Hello friends,
I Sumit Bhandari welcome you from Health Insurance.com.
Thank you very much
for watching this video.  Our topic today is
ICSC Lamb Elevate Care Supreme and
Ultimate Care then we have a product like
HDFC or go opt in Secure or Neevapa ka
Ratio 2.0 so we will compare all these policies a little
over one or two points.
See, in the last few days we have
uploaded fewer videos but many people are
repeatedly
getting the same message on WhatsApp that people require me to take
this Elevate policy of ICICI.  The
DIBPA ratio is 2.0.  There is
Secure Policy of HDFC RGO or Supreme Plan of K.
Ok?  So
what good will these policies do for me?  See,
in health insurance, first of all we have to
select a policy.  Remember one fundamental
principle that the insurance
company, you and your insurance agent, all
three of you have to sit together and first
define your risk.  When you
define your risk,
you have an objective set accordingly that now
I need this policy to cover this risk
or I need this type of solution.  The
solution you have defined
means I have so much money in my pocket.  I want to
buy this.  This is my requirement.  Then
you go out to research in the market to find out
which product is
most suitable for me to diagnose this problem.  Now let's
talk about small points.  ICICI LBRD is
offering a concept within the Elevate plan
that you take this type of rider with us
and we will keep giving you bonuses throughout your life.
Now, the concept of this type is
Nivapa's Ratio 2.0, by adding Platinum Titanium in it, the
concept is that we will increase
your policy 10 times.  So a
consumer thinks that I have taken a policy of Rs 10 lakh.
This will definitely be worth Rs 1 crore.
Greed arises.  Similarly, you have another
product like HDFC's Optima Secure.
The special thing about Optima Secure was
that if you take a policy of Rs 10 lakh, then
within a few years, let us assume that
it becomes around 50 lakh 5 times.  So there
is a similar concept in Care, like
in Ultimate Care, that you will be
given unlimited type infinite bonus.
When did this concept of bonus come into existence?   Let's
talk a little about history.
20 years ago, 25 years ago, only government
companies had policies.  At that time, there was
a norm in those policies that
if you have taken the policy today, if you do
not make a claim then the bonus that will be given to you will be
only 5%.  Remember, there was inflation at that time
too.
Now, to counter the concept of 5% bonus that was given, a
new
concept came up that if you do not make a claim, if there is
no claim in your policy for a year, then the company is giving you a discount in the form of bonus.  This
means
your premium will be slightly lower next year.  See,
in 99% of all policies this was around 5%
only.  What is the next concept
in insurance?  That we will
give you 10% bonus under your policy.  In those days,
20 years ago, it was considered a big thing
that within 5 years we will increase your
bonus by 50%.  What was the third concept
?  The third concept that came up was that
if you claim the bonus of your policy,
because when the company gave the bonus,
they also suffered some loss.  At that time, the
value of ₹4 lakh was a lot.  This is what I am talking about.  I am
talking about 2006-7-8.   At
that time the concept came that if you do
not take the claim then you will score 10-10%.
Within 5 years the bonus became 50%, which means
my policy worth Rs 3 lakh will be worth Rs 4.5 lakh within a few years.
So at that time the concept was
that if you have taken a claim, then on
taking your claim it should be reduced by 200% i.e. 20%.
That means if you do not take the claim then the
company used to give you 10% bonus.  And if
you had taken the claim, it would have reduced it by 20%.  All these
concepts are
not very old.  This was what happened in the industry till 2012.
Then a new revolution
came in the industry in terms of marketing gaming.
This biggest transition happened
around October 2000 to November 2012 when
a product came into the market which said that
if you do not take a claim, then
your bonus will be increased by 50% in one go next year.
If you do not make a claim for two years,
your policy will be doubled within 2 years.
So naturally this policy was
sold very well in the market.
With this, two problems arose at that time.
What used to happen before this?  If you have taken a policy before 2012, then
approximately in three, four or five years, the
premium of your policy used to
increase by around 10% to 15%.  Many companies used to
keep the premium fixed for 10-10 years.
Why?  Your policy was worth Rs 3 lakh.
Then can you imagine that
till 2010 the maximum coverage in the market was
around Rs 10 lakh only.
Considered a very big thing.  The
maximum cover that the company had was
not more than Rs 5 lakh.  This was just 15
years ago.  So in those days we used to
think that what difference will this new concept of bonus make
in the market
?  The difference was that there was a
competition among private companies to
compete with this concept and other
companies also started giving higher bonuses.  It was
not that there was a
requirement for this thing in the market.  There was
a greed among the people in the market that if I do
not take the claim then my policy will
double within 2 years.  Along with this, a
concept of timely restoration came into existence
that if your entire sum assured and bonus is exhausted
then your policy
is restored.  Because of these two concepts, a
big problem arose in our insurance company which exists even today,
that is, the insurance
premium which used to increase by 10% or 12
or 13% after every 4 years.  Now it started getting revised every 2 years.
Right?  Then
a law was passed.  Along with this, there was a
problem inside the industry.  If
by chance you have made a very big claim.
Suppose you had a policy of Rs 3 lakh.
Now I am talking about something that happened more than 15 years ago.
If your policy was for ₹1
lakh and you made a claim of around ₹2 lakh, then
your company would
put loading on the next renewal.
You were charged more money.  You know if there was a
policy but
you were charged 200% or 300% premium then the
government stopped this thing.  Now, the
concept was that your premium would be
increased or loading would be taken while taking the premium.
Three things happened a
lot with this.  The bonus was the same, 5-10%.   The
premium would increase by 10-12%, 7-8% within three to four years.  And thirdly, whenever
someone took a personal policy,
if your age was above 45,
all the insurance companies in India would get your health checkup done.
Then what concept has come in the last 101 years that
companies are telling you all these policies today like
Supreme or Ultimate plan of ICIC Elevate Care
or Secure plan of HDFC Ago or
2.0 plan of NIIB, Ratio 2.0, what are all these plans
telling you?  These plans are saying
that today you take a policy of Rs 10 lakh or
within a few years we will consider your policy as Rs 50 lakh
or you will get bonus within it.
Let's take an example.  The
gold rate was around ₹3035,000 around 2019.
Right?  So today it has become three times that.  You do
n't have to mention this thing in your calculations.
Now these policies are telling you
that we will increase your policy many times.  That
means a greed has come in your mind that
I have taken a policy of Rs 10 lakh and all these
companies will increase my policy many times.
So there is a greed in the mind that
I have got the deal.  What happens?
Understand this thing.  I took a policy of Rs 10 lakh.
Suppose within a few years
it will be Rs 50 lakh.
So if you receive a
claim of Rs 40 lakh, the insurance company will have to pay it.
When today you are going to buy a policy in the market, then
a policy in
which the bonus is very small i.e. 10, 15, 20,
25%.  Suppose that policy was worth ₹00.
When you take a 5x 10x policy
or an unlimited bonus type policy,
then naturally you will not get that policy for ₹00,
that is ₹24 or ₹25000. Firstly, you
pay the extra premium from your side in advance, that is,
you have paid more premium.
Secondly, when the policy of ₹10 lakh becomes of ₹50 lakh, then
when its cover claim comes, the
company will have to pay ₹40 lakh, but when the
company collects that money from the market, at that time it is
selling the policy of ₹10 lakh only.  Understand this thing.
If an insurance company today
bought some insurance risk from you for ₹1 lakh
and you paid a premium of ₹10 lakh.
You took a writer wider by paying 5-10% extra and made
it 10 times.   It was increased
five times or the
amount was already 5x in the policy.  When that policy was of Rs 50 lakh
and the money that was coming
into the company's account, it was
raising money from the market only at the rate of Rs 10 lakh.
When the company's liability is five times or
ten times or infinite times its
liability, then when it makes a claim to the company,
where will it get the money from?  Money
collected from the market will be given as per Rs 10 lakh and
claims of Rs 40-50 lakh or Rs 1 crore in the coming time.  So
from whose pocket will that claim of Rs 1 crore come?  So here
you have to understand this thing.  All these
plans whose names we have mentioned,
one or two of which have come recently, which are
in the industry for four years, are giving you huge
bonuses.  Inside this you
will see a trend.  Whereas till 2007-2010 or
even 2011-12, the premium in your policy used to
increase by only 10-12% within three-four-five years.
People were surprised by that too.  Today,
this right to premium is
coming to you every year.  You have an expensive one
called White Elephant which looks very nice in your house.  You have
raised an elephant but you will also have to feed it.
So,
I do
not normally say that any of these policies are bad.
If you want to take such a policy today then
understand.  Look at the
last 5 years track record of HDFC Ergo Optima Secure to see
how rapidly the premium of this policy has increased.
Although the Reshore policy of NIBM has a huge
sublimit of ₹1 lakh on modern treatment like
robotic surgery, which is a very
derogatory step,
but see, the premium of these policies is
increasing at such a speed.
When you compare these policies today,
because today when you are buying this product, the
company never promises you
that your premium will always remain fixed.
You must have thought that by
taking a policy of Rs 10 lakh, I have got a deal of Rs 50 lakh, Rs 1 crore or
unlimited type.
You feel that you are very smart
and you are fine, you people are smart too.
I don't refuse to put that thing inside.  But the
insurance company never
tells you that it can increase your premium every year.
So, check the premium record of such a product in the last three to four years.  For example, suppose
you have decided to buy HDFC Organo
Optima Secure policy.
Ask the person from whom you are buying the policy to
tell you the premium growth of this policy in the last 5 years.   There used to be a
very good company in India called
Apollo, when HDFCO bought it,
what was the condition of that company after that, a
lot of policies were sold and today if you
see the statistics of IIT, how much premium of HDFC Ago last
year, how much percentage has the overall decline of
HDFC Ago, which is a general insurance company, happened in the year 2023-24 as
compared to 2024-25.
People are not able to pay the money.  Ok
?  Look at Neeb, the product is so amazing.
They will give it five times
, ten times.  Has the company
written to you anywhere that your
premium will remain fixed?  You can
also avail the feature by locking the clock inside it.  It
is clearly written inside it.  Your age
is fixed inside it.  The premium is not fixed.  But
when you buy a policy, greed arises in your mind and
sometimes your intelligence gets clouded.  At
that time we feel that
now my premium for this policy is fixed.   The
premium is not fixed.  Read carefully the
terms and conditions, inside it there
is a clock for your lock.  There are many big
companies like ICICI Lambar which is the
number one player in private general insurance in India.  So you wonder how
he is able to launch such a cheap plan.
Look at his last 5-seven year old products.  The policy which was 5 years older than this policy was
expensive.   Check out the
premium of its comprehensive plan.  What
happened today that the HD ICC LBAD policy which was 7 years
old, the premium which was 7 years ago is
less than the premium today in 2025.  How is
it possible?  So the
most open secret in insurance is that when you are
entering into a policy, you get
greedy and today you are sitting and
comparing that this policy has
this and that, you do not know
what has happened in the industry in the last 25 years and the most open secret that
I was talking about is that
when you are entering into a policy in insurance,
then no company promises you
that how much the premium will increase in the next year, so the
person from whom you are buying the policy.
Ask about its record for the last 5-7 years,
brother, how many times the premium has increased in this product.
If that policy
is only one year old then be careful.  Check the track record
of that company from its previous products.
If you want to
you really want to do research, this is the
way to do research.
Check the previous track record of any company and see
how you increased its premiums in the last 7, 8 or 10 years
or which
policy was launched and which policy will be discontinued now.  That is the
right way to do research.  Yes, if
you were expecting this type of premium x, this
type of video, then yes,
I will tell you that this is included in this policy.
This is what is inside this policy.  Sorry you have
come to the wrong place.  If I wasted your time,
I apologize for that.
But see, the truth is bitter.  You are the
head of your family.  Ok?  You
think you can define your risk.
You think you can underwrite your policy.
You think that you
can buy your policy online
and without reading its proposal form and
without keeping a copy of the proposal form.  You
can take the policy without medical checkup.  So my dear friend,
you are under a big misunderstanding.  If
you have to do research, do it properly.
What is the problem when trying to buy a policy?  You talk to friends.  You
collect some details from the internet.
Whatever you have received is
just information.
This is not knowledge.  There is a difference between knowledge and information.
The more information you
collect, the more confused you will become.
You need knowledge to extract the good things from that garbage, the things that were suitable for me.  Knowledge is
needed.  So, whenever you are buying a policy from any person,
whether you are buying it online,
whether you are buying it from an insurance agent
or a customer care
executive or
buying it directly from the company,
check there and ask that person that brother,
how will you help me at the time of claim, how are the
claims of this policy rejected, how has the
premium of this policy been done in the last 5-7 years,
if you do not
ask the right questions, then you will fall into the script of the other person,
he will cheat you in such a way
that you will not even realize it.
Maximum people who are troubled in the last 5 years are
troubled due to claim rejection.  Do you know that today the
company has
started hiring private investigators for your claims?  At
one time there were medical claims
investigators.  Today, private
investigators will come to your house in twos and
even ask for your Google location.  This
insurance is a very simple product.
What simple product means is that
I pay the money and the company will give me the claim.
This is where its simplicity ends.
This is a legal matter for him.   There
is commercial risk.  Doctors are involved.
Your body is involved and there are many loop
holes where you will
not be given any information.  Everything is into
grey.  If you think you want to read in black and white, then
you will have to spend a few weeks
reading the terms and conditions of the policy.
So my request to everyone is that do
not get trapped in this propaganda and narrative.  Just yesterday, there was a doctor who was
our 13-14 year old client.
He asked if I
could buy an Ekko policy?  It is very cheap.  So
I told the doctor that doctor sahib, please
look at the track of his past claim ratio, how many claims have been given and
how many claims have been rejected and
how the reputation has been built after making these claims legally.
Understand that claim rejection, claim
reputation, these things are different.  This
is not such a simple field.  If you
feel that you can
buy the policy yourself after doing research, then you can do it.  But
for this you will have to give at least two-three months
time.  What will happen otherwise?
Quacks are dangerous. We do not understand the
data that is coming to you on the basis of what Google is telling us.
You know that
under the claim settlement ratio,
look in the financial sheets of the companies and see how many
crores of rupees worth of claims are rejected and they
tell you on the internet that we have
100% claim settlement ratio.  Whereas
inside it is written claim settlement ratio
for a specified period for last 90
days.  How many claims were rejected within the first 90 days
?  Your company received claims of Rs 1 lakh.  Out of that,
80,000 claims were given.
If the company pays those 80,000 claims within the first 3
months, then nowadays the company
tells them that we have 100% claim
settlement ratio and star conditions apply
for a specific period.  So, do
you want to watch any of our weekly videos in this manner, in
which we will
not give you any practical suggestions which are the best part
of the industry?  Will say bitter
things.  Some people will like it.
Maximum people will not like it and
those who have liked it, kindly like the video and
share it with your friends. If you feel like it, then
subscribe to the channel. We are also
posting our videos on health
insurance. It is a good English channel, you
can subscribe to that too. If any person
feels like consulting, then
visit health insurance on our website.
Come on, you took out your precious time to watch this video.
Thank you very much for being connected with this video till this time. Jai Jai
Shri Radhe Aa Aa